Guide to the Timothy H. O'Sullivan Photographs, 1868-1873 RL.00982
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Timothy H. O'Sullivan photographs
1868-1873
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
O'Sullivan, Timothy H., 1840-1882
RL.00982
1.6 Linear Feet
Timothy H. O'Sullivan was an important early American photographer who participated in two geographical surveys of the American West. Collection includes thirty-five gold-toned albumen prints made from glass plate negatives. O'Sullivan made these photographs as part of the King and Wheeler surveys between 1868 and 1873. Main subjects of the photographs are geological and geographical features of Arizona, California, Nevada, Utah, and Wyoming. Collection also contains four photographs of mining operations and two photographs of the Zuni Pueblo in New Mexico.
35 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Timothy H. O'Sullivan Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1972.
These and other photographs by western expeditionary photographers were purchased from Lowdermilk's bookstore in Washington, D.C. prior to its liquidation.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1840 Born in Ireland
circa 1856-1861 Apprenticed under Mathew Brady and Alexander Gardner
1861-1865 Photographed the Civil War, sometimes for Matthew Brady and Alexander Gardner
1867-1869, 1872 Photographed for the King Expedition
1870 Became photographer for the Darien Survey, which explored possible routes for the Panama Canal
1871, 1873-1875 Photographed for the Wheeler Expedition
1880 Appointed official photographer for the U.S. Treasury Department, but retired shortly thereafter for health reasons
1882 Jan. 14 Died at West Brighton, Staten Island, N.Y.
Collection Overview
During his brief career, Timothy H. O'Sullivan made many compelling photographs, and in doing so established himself as one of the most important figures in early American photography. This collection includes thirty-five gold-toned albumen prints, resulting from glass plate negatives O'Sullivan made as he photographed the American west for the King and Wheeler surveys between 1868 and 1873. The geological and geographical features of Arizona, California, Nevada, Utah, and Wyoming are the subjects most heavily represented in this collection. The collection also contains four photographs of mining operations and two photographs of the Zuni Pueblo in New Mexico. The collection is arranged into two series: the King Expeditions Series and the Wheeler Expeditions Series. Both series are arranged chronologically.
Clarence King's Expedition officially bore the title: "The Geological Exploration of the 40th Parallel." King planned to explore a hundred-mile wide swath from the eastern slopes of the Sierra Nevada Mountains across the Great Basin to the Rocky Mountains, eastern Colorado to the California line. This collection includes nine photographs from King's expeditions in 1868 (1), 1869 (6), and 1872 (2).
In 1871, George Montague Wheeler, topographical engineer, took charge of "The Survey of the Territory of the United States West of the 100th Meridian." The field work conducted for this survey involved fourteen trips during 1871-1879. The primary object of the survey was to complete topographical mapping of the country, much of it largely unexplored, but the scope of the work eventually extended to include exhaustive investigation of geological, zoological, and ethnological matters. Publication of the definitive Report upon United States Geographical Surveys West of the One-Hundredth Meridian took place between 1875 and 1889. O'Sullivan made photographs on several of these expeditions. This series includes 26 photographs, from the expeditions of 1871 (18) 1873 (8).
More so than other western expeditionary photographers, Timothy O'Sullivan explored alternative strategies of photographic composition. O'Sullivan created unique compositions through the conscious ordering and visual presentation of bold forms, which emphasized the abstract qualities of the landscape. Several photographs in this collection reveal the formal qualities of O'Sullivan's photographs. These images contrast with the great volume of more picturesque landscapes made by other western expeditionary photographers, although O'Sullivan did make a number of photographs that emphasized natural beauty over form. O'Sullivan was also interested in recording evidence of human interaction with the environment. For example THO.P17 juxtaposes the passing of geological time with evidence of recent human explorations. A photograph also contained in this collection, and of intrinsic interest, THO.P15, reveals visible brush strokes providing evidence of the technique used to coat glass plate negatives.
Related Material
The following collections in the Duke University David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library may contain related material:
William Bell Photographs, 1872 John K. Hillers Photographs, 1871-1889 and undated William Henry Jackson Photographs, 1869-1878 and undated
Photographs; Albumen prints; West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; West (U.S.) -- Discovery and exploration; Southwest, New -- Pictorial works; Southwest, New -- Discovery and exploration; Landscape photography -- West (U.S.); Photographers; Documentary Photography; O'Sullivan, Timothy H., 1840-1882; O'Sullivan, Timothy H., 1840-1882; Wheeler, George M. (George Montague), 1842-1905; Geographical Survey (U.S.); King, Clarence, 1842-1901
- King Expeditions Series, 1868-1872, 1 box
  - 1868 "120" (lower right corner) Lake Marian, Summits of East Humboldt Mountains, Nevada, 8 x 11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.1, Print THO.P1)
    General note
    (source: similar to No. 123 in American Frontiers, p. 83, but from a different angle.)
  - 1869 "16" (lower left corner) Echo Canyon, Utah. Tertiary Bluffs., 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.1, Print THO.P2)
    (source: comparison with Plate 63, Vol. I, of bound photographs of King Survey, National Archives)
    Scope and Contents
    National Archives Number: 77-KN-16
  - 1869 "18" (lower right corner) Tertiary Conglomerates, Weber Valley, Utah., 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.1, Print THO.P3)
    (source: In American Frontiers, p.69)
  - 1869 Tertiary Conglomerates, Weber Valley, Utah., 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.1, Print THO.P4)
    (source: by comparison with THO.P3)
  - 1869 Cottonwood Lake, Wasatch Range, Utah., 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.1, Print THO.P5)
    (source: In American Frontiers, p. 100, but from a different angle)
  - The Falls of the Provo in Utah. Probably 1869., 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.1, Print THO.P6)
    (source: similar to No. 102 in Timothy O'Sullivan, America's Forgotten Photographer, p. 176.
  - Mount Agassiz in Utah. Probably 1869., 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.1, Print THO.P7)
    (source: different angle from view in Timothy O'Sullivan, America's Forgotten Photographer, p.178)
  - 1872 Cañon of Lodore, Green River, Wyoming., 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.1, Print THO.P8)
    (source: comparison with Plate 51, Vol.1, of bound photographs of King Survey, National Archives. Original negative number was 72.)
  - 1872 "50" (lower right corner) Horseshoe Canyon, Green River, Wyoming., 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.1, Print THO.P9)
    (source: the lower left corner of this photograph matches part of the scene in the view on p. 99 in American Frontiers. Silting on the edges of the river is identical.)
    Existence and Location of Copies note
    copy negative available: THO.N9
- Wheeler Expeditions Series, 1871, 1873, 3 boxes
  - 1871 "No. 1. Snow Peaks, Bull Run Mining District, Nevada", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.1, Print THO.P10)
  - 1871 "No. 4. Black Cañon, Colorado River, Looking Below From Big Horn Camp", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.1, Print THO.P11)
  - 1871 "No. 6. Black Cañon, Colorado River, Looking Below, Near Camp 7", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.2, Print THO.P12)
    copy negative available: THO.N12
  - 1871 "No. 7. Black Cañon, Colorado River, Looking Below, Near Camp 7", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.2, Print THO.P13)
  - 1871 "No. 10. Entrance to Black Cañon, Colorado River", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.2, Print THO.P14)
  - 1871 "No. 12. Cereus Giganteus, Arizona", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.2, Print THO.P15)
  - 1871 "No. 13. Water Rhyolites, Near Logan Springs, Nevada", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.2, Print THO.P16)
  - 1871 "No. 14. Rock Carved by Drifiting Sand, Below Fortification Rock, Arizona", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.2, Print THO.P17)
  - 1871 "No. 15. Iceberg Cañon, Colorado River, Looking Above", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.2, Print THO.P18)
  - 1871 "No.16. Alpine Lake in the Sierra Nevada, California", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.2, Print THO.P19)
    Appears as a print in Wheeler's Report upon United States Geographical Surveys West of the One Hundreth Meridian Vol. I, p. 40 (plate II).
  - 1871 "No. 94. Music Mt. From Truxton Springs, A. T., Arizona Series", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.2, Print THO.P20)
  - 1871 No. 7. Fifteen Stamp Mill, Mineral Hill, Nevada, 8 x 10.5 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board. (Box THO.2, Print THO.P21)
    National Archives number: 106-WB-29
  - 1871 No.13. Canfield's Mill, Belmont, Nevada, 8 x 10.5 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board. (Box THO.2, Print THO.P22)
    copy negative available: THO.N22
    National Archives Number: 106-WB-13
  - 1871 No. 28. Quartz Formation near Silver Cañon, Pahranaget, Lake District, Nevada, 8 x 10.5 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board. (Box THO.2, Print THO.P23)
    National Archives number 106-WB-27
  - 1871 No. 47. Meadow Valley Mining Co.'s Works, Dry Valley, Nevada, 8 x 10.5 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board. (Box THO.3, Print THO.P24)
    National Archives number 106-WB-47
  - 1871 Combination Mill, Belmont, Nevada., 8 x 10.5 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board. (Box THO.3, Print THO.P25)
    National Archives number 106-WB-12
  - 1871 Death Valley, California. In Timothy O'Sullivan, America's Forgotten Photographer, p. 242, 8 x 10.5 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board. (Box THO.3, Print THO.P26)
  - 1871 No. 65. Quartz Formation near Silver Cañon Pahranaget, Lake District Nevada. Or Part of Hyko Mining District Nevada. Left side overlaps with right side of No. 28, 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.3, Print THO.P27)
    National Archives number 106-WB-65
  - 1873 "No. 1. Apache Lake, Sierra Blanca Range, Arizona", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.3, Print THO.P28)
  - 1873 "No. 2. View on Apache Lake, Sierra Blanca Range, Arizona", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.3, Print THO.P29)
  - 1873 "No. 4. North Fork Cañon, Sierra Blanca Creek, Arizona", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.3, Print THO.P30)
  - 1873 "No. 8. Historic Spanish Record of the Conquest, South Side of Inscription Rock, N.M.", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.3, Print THO.P31)
  - 1873 "No. 12. Looking Across the Colorado River to Mouth of Paria Creek", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.3, Print THO.P32)
  - 1873 "No. 16. Head of Cañon de Chelle, Looking Down, Walls about 1200 feet in height" [Arizona], 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.3, Print THO.P33)
    copy negative available: THO.N33
  - 1873 "No. 17. Indian Pueblo, Zuni, N.M. View from the South", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.3, Print THO.P34)
  - 1873 "No. 18. Old Mission Church, Zuni Pueblo, N.M. View from the Plaza", 8 x 10.75-11 inch print mounted on a 16 x 20 inch board (Box THO.3, Print THO.P35)